Henry W. Leung Ph.D.

Astronomy & Astrophysics Researcher at the University of Toronto Toronto, Ontario, Canada

• henrysky.github.io

➤ henryskyleung@gmail.com

• henrysky

in Henry Leung

Bilingual in English & Chinese

⟨⟩ Python & C

Canadian & Hong Konger

SUMMARY

I am a recent PhD graduate in Astronomy & Astrophysics from the University of Toronto, with a focus on applying advanced deep learning techniques to build multi-modal foundation models for science. My research aimed to analyze large, cross-domain datasets from multiple surveys, contributing to a deeper understanding of the formation history and dynamics of the Milky Way Galaxy. I am committed to open science, with the majority of my code and models being well-tested, well-documented, and openly available to the community. I am looking forward to apply my expertise in machine learning, data analysis, and software development to solve complex industry problems and drive innovation.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

University of Toronto

Sept 2019 - Oct 2024

Graduate Researcher & Data Science Institute Doctoral Fellow

- Led an independent, data-driven research program, integrating cutting-edge deep learning techniques such as Transformers, Denoising Diffusion models, and Large Language Models (LLMs) to develop multi-modal foundation models for scientific applications.
- Created and maintained robust, well-documented, and thoroughly tested open-source software mainly written in Python, C and SQL, contributing both to personal projects and to the wider scientific community.
- Delivered spotlight talks and posters at major conferences, including NeurIPS, ICML, and ESA AI in Astronomy, and collaborated with community-led initiatives like the Multimodal Universe project.
- Curated a value-added catalogue of deep learning-derived stellar parameters and uncertainties, for the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) collaboration.
- Built and optimized machine learning models using frameworks like PyTorch and TensorFlow trained on large astronomical datasets, leveraging tools such as Docker and Postgresql as well as deploying them on Canada's research supercomputing clusters Narval equipped with Nvidia A100 GPUs.
- Peer-reviewing articles in journals like American Astronomical Society journal.
- Mentored undergraduate students in research projects, providing guidance on data analysis, software development, and scientific writing.

University of Toronto

Jan 2018 - Dec 2024

Teaching Assistant

- Developed homework assignments, including multiple choice questions and Python modules. Assisted with grading Python codes, written lab reports, and term projects.
- Led weekly tutorials and practical lab sessions, providing instructional support and clarifying course concepts.

 Answered student queries via email and discussion boards.
- Organized and hosted review/help sessions, invigilated midterms/exams and observation nights at the campus observatory.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Astronomy & Astrophysics, University of Toronto

2020 - 2024

Dissertation: "Exploring the Milky Way with Deep Learning" with Prof. Jo Bovy

M.Sc. in Astronomy & Astrophysics, University of Toronto

2019 - 2020

H.B.Sc. in Physics & Astronomy, University of Toronto

2014 - 2019

PUBLICATION OVERVIEW

I am an author on 14 referred papers that have 2560+ citations (h-index=11). Excluding 2 collaboration papers, there are 12 referred papers that have 760+ citations. Details of my ORCID (0000-0002-0036-2752) associated publications can be accessed on Astrophysics Data System (ADS). Some publications are also accepted for talks and posters at various conferences (see this Section).

CONFERENCE

My research has been presented at various international conferences and workshops. Here are some of the highlights:

NeurIPS (Neural Information Processing Systems)

Vancouver, Canada

Datasets and Benchmarks Track

December 2024

Collaboration Poster on "The Multimodal Universe: Enabling Large-Scale Machine Learning with 70TBs of Astronomical Scientific Data"

ICML (International Conference on Machine Learning)

Vienna, Austria

Organized by Workshop on Foundation Models in the Wild

July 2024

Poster on "Estimating Probability Densities with Transformer and Denoising"

NeurIPS (Neural Information Processing Systems)

New Orleans, US

Organized by Machine Learning and the Physical Sciences Workshop

Dec 2023

Talk on "Towards an Astronomical Foundation Model for Stars"

Debating the Potential of Machine Learning in Astronomical Surveys

New York, US

Organized by Flatiron Institute & Institut Astrophysique de Paris

Nov 2023

Talk on "Towards an Astronomical Foundation Model for Stars with a Transformerbased Model"

Artificial Intelligence for Astronomy

Garching, Germany

Organized by European Southern Observatory (ESO)

July 2019

Talk on "Mapping the Milky Way Galaxy with Deep Learning"

SOFTWARE OVERVIEW

Most of my research are open-sourced including codes for publications: https://github.com/henrysky. This includes a few software packages used by the community that are well tested using continuous integration with GitHub Actions and well documented with docstrings and user guides, for example:

astroNN (7)

Deep Learning for Astronomers with Keras

Galaxv10

A CIFAR10-like galaxy image dataset for educational and research purposes

milkyway_plot 🦸

A handy visualization tool ge for plotting face-on and all-sky MilkyWay with Matplotlib and Bokeh

MyGaiaDB 🜎

A data management package to setup local serverless multi-terabytes astronomical databases using SQLite and run query locally with Python